Puzzles
الألغاز
and magic.
وألعاب الخفة.
I work in what most people think
أعمل فيما يظنه معظم الناس
are two distinct fields,
حقلين مختلفين،
but I believe they are the same.
ولكنني أعتقد أنهما متماثلان.
I am both a magician and
أنا في نفس الوقت ساحرٌ
a New York Times crossword puzzle constructor,
ومنشئ كلماتٍ متقاطعةٍ بمجلة نيويورك تايمز،
which basically means I've taken
مما يعني أنني قمت باختيار
the world's two nerdiest hobbies
أكثر هوايتين معقدتين
and combined them into one career.
ودمجتهما في مهنة واحدة
And I believe that magic and puzzles are the same
وأعتقد أن السحر والألغاز هما الشيء نفسه
because they both key into one of
لأنهما يهدفان الى واحدة
the most important human drives:
من أهم الدوافع الإنسانية:
the urge to solve.
الحاجة لإيجاد الحل.
Human beings are wired to solve,
البشر متعلقون بإيجاد الحل
to make order out of chaos.
على خلق النظام انطلاقا من الفوضى.
It's certainly true for me.
هذا حقيقي جدًا بالنسبة لي.
I've been solving my whole life.
فأنا أقوم بإيجاد الحل طوال حياتي.
High school consisted of epic Scrabble matches in the cafeteria
كانت أيامي في الثانوية مليئة بمباريات سكرابل ملحمية بالمقصف
and not really talking to girls,
ولم تكن فيها محادثات مع البنات
and then at about that time
وفي ذلك الوقت
I started learning magic tricks
بدأت بتعلم الحيل السحرية
and definitely not talking to girls.
وقطعًا لم تكن فيها محادثات مع البنات.
There's nothing like starting a conversation with,
لبدء الحديث، ما من جملة أفضل من
"Hey, did you know that 'prestidigitation' is worth
"مرحبًا، هل تعلم أن كلمة "الشعوذة" تعادل
20 points in Scrabble?"
20 نقطة في سكرابل؟"
But back then, I noticed an intersection
ولكن، لاحظت نقطة تقاطع
between puzzles and illusion.
بين الألغاز والوهم.
When you do the crossword puzzle
عندما تقوم بحل الكلمات المتقاطعة
or when you watch a magic show,
أو تشاهد عرضًا لألعاب الخفة،
you become a solver,
تصبح موجدا للحل
and your goal is to try to find the order in the chaos,
ويصبح هدفك هو محاولة إيجاد الترتيب انطلاقا من الفوضى،
the chaos of, say, a black-and-white puzzle grid,
فوضى كتلك الموجودة في شبكة الكلمات المتقاطعة
a mixed-up bag of Scrabble tiles,
أو حقيبة مليئة بمكعبات السكرابل المخلوطة
or a shuffled pack of playing cards.
أو مجموعة من أوراق اللعب المخلوطة.
And today, as a cruciverbalist —
واليوم، بما أنني محترف في ألغاز الكلمات المتقاطعة--
23 points —
23 نقطة--
and an illusion designer, I create that chaos.
وصانع أوهام، فإني أُحدث تلك الفوضى.
I test your ability to solve.
وأختبر قدرتكم على الحل.
Now, it turns out research tells us
حاليا، كشف بحث
that solving is as primal as eating and sleeping.
أن الحل حاجة بدائيّة مثل الأكل والنوم.
From birth, we are wired to solve.
منذ الولادة، نحن متعلقون بإيجاد الحل.
In one UCLA study, newborns still in the hospital
في جامعة كاليفورنيا أجريت دراسة على حديثي الولادة في المستشفى
were shown patterns, patterns like this:
حيث عُرضت عليهم أشكال مثل:
circle, cross, circle, cross.
دائرة، علامة، دائرة، علامة.
And then the pattern was changed: triangle, square.
ثم تحول الشكل الى: مثلث، مربع.
And by tracking an infant's gaze,
وبتتبع نظرة الرضيع،
we know that newborns as young as a day old
عرفنا أن حديثي الولادة مثلهم مثل الكبار
can notice and respond to disruptions in order.
يمكنهم الملاحظة والاستجابة لا خلل في الترتيب.
It's remarkable.
إنه رائع.
So from infancy through old age,
فلذا من الطفولة وصولًا للأعمار المتقدمة،
the urge to solve unites us all,
الرغبة في ايجاد الحل توحدنا جميعًا،
and I even found this photo on Instagram
وجدت هذه الصورة على الإنستقرام
of pop star Katy Perry solving a crossword puzzle
لنجمة البوب "كاتي بيري" وهي تحل الكلمات المتقاطعة
with her morning coffee.
وهي تشرب قهوتها الصباحية.
Like.
إعجاب.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now, solving exists across all cultures.
حاليا، ايجاد الحل موجود في كل الثقافات.
The American invention is the crossword puzzle,
الاختراع الامريكي هو الكلمات المتقاطعة،
and this year we are celebrating
وهذه السنة نحن نحتفل
the 100th anniversary of the crossword puzzle,
بالذكرى ال 100 للكلمات المتقاطعة،
first published in The New York World.
نُشرت للمرة الأولى في صحيفة نيويورك العالمية
But many other cultures have their signature puzzles as well.
لكن ثقافات أخرى عديدة لديها ألغازها الخاصة.
China gives us tangrams,
الصين لديها لعبة التانجرام،
which would test solvers' abilities
التي تختبر قدرة الحلَالين
to form shapes from the jumbled pieces.
لتكوين أشكال من قطع مختلطة.
Chaos. Order.
فوضى. ترتيب.
Order.
ترتيب.
And order.
وترتيب.
That one's my favorite, let's hear it again.
هذه هي المفضلة لدي، لنسمعها مرة أخرى.
Okay.
حسنًا.
And how about this puzzle
وماذا عن هذا اللغز
invented in 18th-century England:
الذي اخترع في القرن ال18 بإنجلترا:
the jigsaw puzzle.
لعبة تركيب القطع.
Is this not making order out of chaos?
هل هذه ليست عمل ترتيب انطلاقا من فوضى؟
So as you can see,
لذا كما لاحظتم،
we are always solving.
نقوم دائما بإيجاد الحل.
We are always trying to decode our world.
نحاول دائمًا فك شفرة عالمنا.
It's an eternal quest.
هذا سعي أبدي.
It's just like the one Cervantes wrote about
مثل كتاب ل"سرفانتس" عن
in "Don Quixote,"
"دون كيشوت"
which by the way is the root of the word "quixotry,"
الذي عمومًا هو جذر كلمة " كويكستري"
the highest-scoring Scrabble word of all time,
أعلى مجموع في لعبة السكرابل في كل الاوقات،
365 points.
365 نقطة.
But anyway, "Don Quixote" is an important book.
ولكن على أي حال، "دون كيشوت" كتاب مهم.
You guys have read "Don Quixote," yes?
أنتم قرأتم "دون كيشوت" صحيح؟
I'm seeing some heads nod.
إنني أرى بعض علامات الموافقة.
Come on guys, really?
هيا يا شباب، حقًا؟
Who's read "Don Quixote?" Let's do this. Raise your hands if you've read "Don Quixote."
من قرأ "دون كيشوت؟" لنفعل هذا. ارفعوا أيديكم إذا قرأتم له.
There we go. Smart audience.
ها نحن. جمهور ذكي.
Who's read "Don Quixote?" Get them up.
من قرأ "دون كيشوت؟"
Okay, good, because I need somebody smart here
حسنًا، جميل، لأنني أحتاج شخصا ذكيا هُنا
because now I'm going to demonstrate
لأنني الآن سأشرح
with the help of one of you
بمساعدة واحد منكم
just how deeply rooted your urge to solve is,
مدى عمق رغبتكم في ايجاد الحل
just how wired to solve all of you really are,
مدى تعلقكم جميعًا بإيجاد الحل،
so I'm going to come into the audience
لذا سآتي الى الجمهور
and find somebody to help me.
وأجد شخصًا ما ليساعدني.
Let's see.
هيا لنرى.
Everybody's looking away all of a sudden.
فجأة الكل ينظر بعيدًا.
Can I? Would you? What is your name? Gwen.
هل يمكنني؟ ما اسمك؟ غوين.
I'm not a mind reader, I can see your name tag.
أنا لست قارئ عقل. أستطيع رؤية اسمك.
Come with me, Gwen. Everyone give her a round of applause, make her feel welcome.
تعالي، جوين حيوها جميعًا. أجعلوها تشعر بالترحيب.
Gwen, after you.
غوين، من بعدك.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Are you so excited?
هل أنت متحمسة؟
Did you know that your name is worth
هل تعلمين أن اسمك يساوي
eight points in Scrabble?
8 نقاط في لعبة السكرابل؟
Okay, stand right here, Gwen, right here.
حسنًا، قفي هنا، يا جوين، هنا.
Now, Gwen, before we begin,
الآن، غوين، قبل أن نبدأ،
I'd like to point out a piece of the puzzle,
أريد أن أُشير الى قطعة من الأحجية،
which is here in this envelope,
التي توجد هُنا في هذا المُغلف،
and I will not go near it. Okay?
وأنا لن أقترب منها، حسنًا؟
And over here we have a drawing of some farm animals.
وهنا لدينا رسمة لبعض حيوانات المزعة.
You can see we have an owl, we have a horse,
ويوجد لدينا بومة، حصان،
a donkey, a rooster, an ox, and a sheep,
حمار، ديك، ثور، خروف،
and then here, Gwen, we have
وهنا، جوين، لدينا
some fancy art store markers,
بعض أقلام الرسم الملونة،
Gwen: Cobalt. David Kwong: Cobalt, yes. Cobalt.
غوين: كوبالت. ديفيد: كوبالت نعم، كوبالت.
But we have a silver, a red, an emerald,
ولكن لدينا قلم فضي، أحمر، زمردي،
and an amber marker,
وقلم كهرماني،
and Gwen, you are going to color this drawing
غوين، أنت ستلونين هذه الرسمة
just like you were five years old,
كما كنت تفعلين في الخامسة من عمرك،
one marker at a time.
استخدمي كل قلم مرة واحدة
It's going to be a lot of fun.
سيكون هذا مسليا.
But I'm going to go over here.
ولكني سأقف هنا.
I don't want to see what you're doing.
لا أريد أن أرى ماذا تفعلينه.
Okay, so don't start yet.
حسنًا، لا تبدئي الآن.
Wait for me to get over here and close my eyes.
انتظري حتى أبتعد لأُغلق عيناي
Now Gwen, are you ready?
الان جوين، هل أنت مستعدة؟
Pick up just one marker, pick up just one marker,
التقطي قلما واحدا فقط،
and why don't you color in the horse for me?
ولم لا تلونين الحصان؟
Color in the horse — big, big, big scribbles,
تلوينا سريعا بلا عناية،
broad strokes, don't worry about staying in the lines.
خطوط عريضة ولا تهتمي بالدقة
All right. Great.
حسنًا. عظيم.
And why don't you take that marker and recap it
خُذي القلم وغطيه
and place it on the table for me.
وضعيه على المنضدة.
Okay, and pick up another marker out of the cup
-حسنًا، خُذي قلما آخر من الكوب
and take off the cap
وانزعي غطاءه
and color in the donkey for me, color in the donkey.
ولوني الحمار،
Big scribbles.
تلوينا بدون دقة
Okay, cool, and re-cap that marker
حسنًا، جيد، غطِي القلم مرة أخرى
and place it on the table.
وضعيه على المنضدة.
And pick up another marker for me
والتقطي قلما آخر
and take off the cap. Isn't this fun?
وانزعي الغطاء.أليس هذا ممتعًا؟
And color in the owl for me.
ولوني البومة.
Color in the owl.
لوني البومة.
Okay, and recap that marker
حسنًا، غطي القلم
and pick up another marker out of the cup
والتقطي قلمًا آخر من الكوب
and color in the rooster for me, color in the rooster.
ولوني الديك.
Good, good, good, good, good.
جميل جدًا
Big, big, big strokes. Good, good.
تلوين بلا عناية. جميل
Pick up another marker out of the cup
التقطِي قلما آخر من الكوب
and color in the ox for me. Color in the ox.
ولوني الثور
Okay, good.
حسنًا، جميل.
A lot of color on that, and recap, and place it on the table,
لونيه بشدة، ثم غطي القلم مجددًا، وضعيه على المنضدة،
and pick up another marker out of the cup.
والتقطِي قلما آخر من الكوب.
Oh, I'm out? Okay, I'm going to turn around.
يا الهى، لقد انتهيت؟ حسنًا سأدور.
Did I forget? Oh, I forgot my purple marker.
هل نسيت؟ يا إلهي. لقد نسيت القلم الأرجواني.
This is still going to work, though.
رغم ذلك، هذا سيفي بالغرض.
I think this is still going to work, mostly.
أعتقد أن هذا سيفي بالغرض، غالبًا.
So Gwen, I'm going to hand you this envelope.
لذا غوين، سأعطيك هذا المُغلف.
Don't open it yet. Do not open it yet,
لا تفتحيه بعد.
but I am going to write down your choices
ولكنني سأدون ما اخترته
so that everybody can see
لذا الكل سيرى
the choices that you made.
الاختيارات التي قمت بها.
Okay, great. So we have a cobalt horse,
حسنًا، جيد. لدينا حصان رمادي،
amber owl,
بومة كهرمانية،
a silver ox,
ثور فضي،
yes, okay, a red donkey,
نعم، حسنًا، حمار أحمر،
and what was the emerald color? A rooster.
وما كان ملونا بالزمردي؟ الديك.
An emerald rooster. Okay.
ديك زمردي، حسنًا.
Now for the moment of truth, Gwen,
الآن لحظة الحقيقة، غوين،
we're going to take a look in that envelope.
سنلقى نظرة على المُغلف.
Why don't you open it up and remove
لماذا لا تفتحيه وتُخرجي
the one piece of paper from inside
الورقة التي بداخله
and hand it to me,
وسلميها لي،
and we will see if it matches your choices.
وسنرى إذا كانت توافق اختياراتك.
Yes, I think it does.
نعم، أعتقد ذلك.
We have a cobalt horse, we have a red donkey,
لدينا حصان كوبالت، حمار أحمر
we have an amber owl, we have an emerald rooster, a silver ox,
بومة كهرمانية، ديك زمردي، ثور فضي،
I forgot my purple marker so we have a blank sheep,
نسيت القلم الأرجواني لذا لدينا خروف بدون لون،
but that's a pretty amazing coincidence, don't you think?
ولكن هذه صدفة مذهلة، ألا تعتقدون
Gwen, well done. That's beautiful. (Applause)
غوين، أحسنتِ. هذا جميل. (تصفيق)
I'll take that back from you.
سآخذ منكِ هذا.
So ladies and gentlemen, how is this possible?
لذا سيداتي وسادتي، كيف يكون هذا ممكنًا؟
How is this possible? Well, could it be
كيف يكون هذا ممكنًا؟ حسنًا، من الممكن
that Gwen's brain is so wired to solve
أن عقل غوين متعلق جدًا بإيجاد الحل
that she decoded hidden messages?
أنها تفك شفرة رسائل مخفية؟
Well this is the puzzle I present to you.
حسنًا هذا اللغز الذي قدمته لكم.
Could there be order
هل يمكن أن يكون هناك ترتيب
in the chaos that I created?
انطلاقا من فوضى في الذي فعلته؟
Let's take a closer look.
هيا بنا نأخذ نظرة أقرب.
Do you recall when I showed you these puzzle pieces?
هل تذكرون عندما عرضت لكم قطع الأحاجي؟
What image did it ultimately become? A cobalt horse.
ما الصورة التي ظهرت؟ حصان كوبالت.
The plot thickens.
المؤامرة تتضخم.
And then we played a game of tangrams
ثم لعبنا لعبة التانجرام
with an emerald rooster.
بديك زمردي.
That one's my favorite.
هذه المفضلة لدي.
And then we had an experiment with a silver ox.
ثم كان لدينا تجربة بالثور الفضي.
And Katy Perry drinks her morning coffee
و"كاتي بيري" التي تشرب قهوتها الصباحية
out of an amber owl.
في كوب بومة كهرماني.
Thank you, Katy, for taking that photo for me.
شكرًا لكِ "كاتي" لالتقاطك الصورة من أجلي.
Oh, and there's one more, there's one more.
وهناك شيء آخر،
I believe you colored a red donkey, Gwen.
أعتقد انكِ لونت الحمار بالأحمر، غوين.
Ladies and gentlemen, could you raise your hands
سيداتي وسادتي، هل يمكنكم رفع أيديكم
for me if you've read "Don Quixote?"
إذا قرأتم "دون كيشوت؟"
Who's read "Don Quixote?" (Laughter)
من قرأ "دون كيشوت؟" (ضحك)
But wait, but wait, wait, wait, wait, there's more.
ولكن انتظروا، هناك المزيد.
There's more.
هناك المزيد.
Gwen, I was so confident
غوين، كنت واثقا جدًا
that you were going to make these choices
أنكِ ستختارين هذه الاختيارات
that I made another prediction,
إنني خمنت تخمينا آخر،
and I put it in an even more indelible place,
ووضعته في مكان متعذر
and it's right here.
وهو هنا.
Ladies and gentlemen,
سيداتي وسادتي،
we have today's New York Times.
لدينا صحيفة اليوم لنيويورك تايمز.
The date is March 18th, 2014.
التاريخ هو 18 مارس 2014.
Many of you in the first couple of rows
مجموعة منكم في الصف الأول
have it underneath your seats as well.
موجودة لديه تحت مقعده.
Really dig. We hid them under there.
ابحثوا جيدًا. خبأناها تحت مقاعدكم.
See if you can fish out the newspaper
حاولوا العثور على الجريدة
and open up to the arts section
وافتحوا القسم الفني
and you will find the crossword puzzle,
ستجدون الكلمات المتقاطعة،
and the crossword puzzle today
والكلمات المتقاطعة لهذا اليوم
was written by yours truly.
كتبت من طرفكم.
You can see my name above the grid.
يمكنكم رؤية اسمي.
I'm going to give this to you, Gwen, to take a look.
سأعطيك هذا يا غوين لتلق نظرة.
And I will also put it up on the screen.
وسأضعه على الشاشة.
Now let's take a look
الآن هيا ننظر
at another piece of the puzzle.
إلى قطعة أخرى من الأحجية.
If you look at the first clue for 1-across,
إذا نظرتم إلى أول مساعدة لأول كلمة
it starts with the letter C, for corrupt,
إنها تبدأ بحرف الفاء لـ فاسد،
and just below that we have an O, for outfielder,
وتحتها لدينا أول حرف من كلمة مُدافع،
and if you keep reading the first letters of the clues down,
وإذا أكملتم قراءة أول حرف من كل مساعدة،
you get cobalt horse,
ستجدون حصان كوبالت،
amber owl, silver ox,
بومة كهرمانية، ثور فضي،
red donkey, and emerald rooster.
حمار أحمر وديك زمردي.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
That's pretty cool, right?
هذا جميل جدًا، صحيح؟
It's The New York Times.
إنها النيويورك تايمز.
But wait, wait, wait, wait. Wait.
ولكن انتظروا،
Oh, Gwen,
غوين
do you recall how I forgot my purple marker,
هل تتذكرين كيف نسيتِ القلم الأرجواني،
and you were unable to color the sheep?
ولم تكوني قادرة على تلوين الخروف؟
Well, if you keep reading
جميل، إذا أكملتم القراءة
starting with 25-down,
بدء من الدليل ال 25،
it says,
إنه يقول،
"Oh, by the way,
“فيما يخص
the sheep can be left blank."
الخروف يمكن أن يُترك بدون تلوين."
(Laughter) (Applause)
(ضحك) (تصفيق)
But wait, wait, wait, there's one more thing,
ولكن انتظروا، هناك شيء آخر،
there's one more thing,
هناك شيء آخر،
there's one final piece of the puzzle.
هناك قطعة أخيرة من الأُحجية.
Gwen, I am so grateful for your choices
غوين، أشكرك جدًا لاختياراتك
because if we take a look
لأننا إذا ألقينا نظرة
at the first letters of your combinations,
على أول حرف لتركيباتك،
we get "C-H-A-O-S" for chaos
نحصل على " ف-و-ض-ى" لفوضى
and "O-R-D-E-R" for order.
و" ت- ر-ت-ي-ب" لترتيب.
That's chaos and order.
هذا هو الفوضى والترتيب.
We've all made order out of chaos.
كلنا نكون الترتيب انطلاقا من الفوضى.
So ladies and gentlemen, the next time
لذا سيداتي وسادتي، المرة المقبلة
you find yourself with a puzzle,
التي تجدون فيها أنفسكم مع أُحجية
whether it's in your life or in your work,
أينما كانت في حياتكم أو عملكم،
or maybe it's at the Sunday morning
أو عند إفطار صباح يوم الأحد
breakfast table with The New York Times,
مع جريدة نيويورك تايمز،
remember, you are all wired to solve.
تذكروا أنكم جميعا متعلقون بإيجاد الحل.
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)